hi welcome back to the channel today we
are going to make the poll winning
selection from our YouTube poll which is
pineapple ice cream
and every couple of weeks I put a poll
on YouTube for people to vote of what
they want me to make
the pineapple ice cream just started to
creep ahead at the end last time I think
the other one was caramel Macadamia
which also sounded excellent I'm gonna
put that one in the next poll
so pineapple
one of those fruits that is can be
really difficult to make into ice cream
because there's a lot of water in it and
people don't really know what to do with
it often they just cut it up and put it
in their ice cream it goes really icy
and a little bit you know
horrible so
what we're going to do is we're going to
buy a pineapple and make some pineapple
ice cream for you today just so you can
see how I make it and hopefully you make
it this way too because it is X
first thing you're going to need to do
is go out and buy a pineapple and you
kind of want it to go not too soft but
ripe you want it to be ripe you don't
want to start doing pineapple ice cream
with a pineapple that is still quite
hard so when it's ready get your thumb
test it make sure that it's starting to
go soft at that point cut the top off
because you're not going to need that
what you're going to need is 250 grams
of pineapple and that is close enough
once that's done you're going to chop
your pineapple into small pieces and put
it in a pan here these pieces are about
one centimeter cubed
once you've got them all chopped up
you're going to put your pan on the hob
get the burner going and you're going to
add in
150 grams of sugar onto that
on top of that 150 grams sugar you're
gonna add in 30 to 50 milliliters of
cold water and what this will do is
start the maceration process of
pulling water out of the pineapple and
you're going to let this warm up to a
soft boil and you're going to leave it
there for 20 to 25 minutes
at that point what you're going to do is
add in a bit of pectin now if you looked
or watched the stabilizer video before
you know that you need to add a
stabilizer to sugar to break up so it
doesn't Clump when you add it into a
liquid that's what I'm going to do here
I'm just going to take a couple of grams
of sugar add in my
three grams of pectin powder
there's a lot of peas in there
and add that into the mix get it nicely
stirred and emulsified and then make
sure that that's completely activated by
leaving it for a further 10 minutes what
you're looking for here is this stage
where without changing the temperature
the actual bubbles start to rise up the
pan on their own that's the indication
that you've burnt off most of the free
water within your mixture
if you're unsure if that's what's
happening then you can just give it a
stir leave it and watch to see if that
happens again and as you can see here
it's boiled up again which means that
most of our free water is gone
that means the stabilizer the pectin in
this case has done its job of
stabilizing free water once it's cooled
down put it into a container just leave
it on the side covered so this is
completely sealed
and let it cool down completely I left
it for 24 hours once your pineapple jam
is completely chilled down you're going
to take your milk and put it in the pan
turn the heat on and you're going to add
in the last remaining bit of sugar
once that's completely dissolved and
your mix is coming up to temperature
you're going to add in all of your
pineapple jam now what I'm going to
recommend here is you do this in two
stages stage one is you drain some of
the sugar syrup out of your mix first
add that in and just gently stir that
that will dissipate the acid that's left
in this mix without curdling your milk
then once that's completely mixed in you
can finally add in the remaining
pineapple jam and give it a nice stir
at that stage take it off the heat and
then put it in a container where you're
going to add in your cream and pop it in
the fridge to completely chill down this
is an unusual mix because the add-in is
already there it's already in the base
now what will happen is it will settle
at the bottom being in the fridge
overnight so you're going to take your
whisk and just gently mix it back up
before popping it in your ice cream
machine to churn
average kind of time 10 to 12 minutes
for me once it's done we're going to
scoop it out pop it in the containers
and then finally we're gonna sling it
into the freezer for four to five hours
to completely harden off pineapple ice
cream
feels about right I like my ice cream to
be scoopable without waiting uh that's a
personal choice I increase sugars and or
dextrose depending on the result that I
want to make it as scoopable as I want
it you're free to do this yourself if a
recipe calls for a certain amount of
sugar and no invert sugar you can
subtract some of that sucrose table
sugar and increase your
invert sugar so dextrose or whatever it
is you might like to use that will just
make it a bit more scoopable so if you
are you know desperate to eat ice cream
you don't have to wait you can just go
to the freezer take it out and eat it so
let's get some scooped up let's see what
this pineapple ice cream turned out like
shall we
nice scoop like I said right amount of
sugar in there for me
it smells great I could smell the
pineapple straight away I can see lots
of little cubes of pineapple in there
which is nice
let's just eat some shall we
[Music]
perfect
really nice creamy ice cream base
a
subtle but not too subtle pineapple
flavor running throughout that ice cream
so again that flavor is coming from
sugar this syrup that you've made your
pineapple jam into
the infusion also of leaving that
pineapple in your base in the fridge
overnight
that's infused that base with that kind
of flavor really really nice
the pineapple chunks they're not icy at
all they're really nice and soft
bursting with pineapple flavor still
juicy almost
oh it's really good really really nice
it's winter it's dark it's cold it's wet
it's miserable
pineapple ice cream takes you somewhere
else it takes you to Summer takes you to
a tropical island somewhere where you
can sip on a pina colada if that's your
kind of thing really nice something to
try and perfect before you get into the
summer warmer months
as always you can support the channel on
Kofi links on the screen and in the
description below thank you for liking
and subscribing as always we will see
you next